A Guide to the Bedford County (Va.) Judgments, 1753-1870
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Bedford County (Va.) Judgments, 1753-1870
The Library of Virginia
1139350-1139437; 1157713-1157714
86.15 cu. ft. (91 boxes)
Bedford County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Bedford County.
Historical Information
Bedford County was formed in 1753 from Lunenburg County. Part of Albemarle was added in 1754 and part of Lunenburg was added later.
The County Court was the original colonial court of adjudication and recordation, and it was the principal tribunal for the administration of local justice. The individual justices could act on small claims matters as well as criminal matters where imminent bodily harm was a possibility, there being an appeal to the full County Court, which met monthly. This court ceased to exist in 1904 and the recordation function was transferred to the circuit court.
The Superior Court of Law was created in 1808. It met twice a year in each county, presided over by a circuit-riding General Court judge. Records were filed with the County Court. It had civil and criminal jurisdiction. The court ceased to exist in 1831.
The Circuit Superior Courts of Law and Chancery, established in 1831, were the upper courts on the local level. Sessions were held twice a year in each county, presided over by a General Court judge. The counties were grouped into districts for the convenience of the judge. The court ceased to exist in 1851.
The Circuit Court was authorized by the Constitution of 1851 and established by an act of the General Assembly passed in May 1852. Courts were held twice yearly in each county, presided over by 21 judges who rode circuits in the area of their jurisdiction. The records were filed with County Court records. These courts were granted original jurisdiction concurrrent with that of the County Courts, as well as appellate jurisdiction in all civil cases of more than fifty dollars and criminal cases not "expressly cognizable in some other court," including those involving loss of life.
Scope and Content
Bedford County (Va.) Judgments, 1753-1870, contain civil cases heard in County Court, Superior Court of Law, Circuit Superior Court, and Circuit Court in which justice was administered on the strictly formulated rules of common law. The majority of cases in this record series relate to matters of debt.
Arrangement
Chronological (Cases filed within each box by month and year they were resolved.)
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Bedford County (Va.)--Circuit Court.; Bedford County (Va.)--Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery.; Bedford County (Va.)--County Court.; Bedford County (Va.)--Superior Court of Law.
Subjects:
Civil procedure--Virginia--Bedford County.; Debt--Virginia--Bedford County.; Public Records--Virginia--Bedford County.
Geographical Names:
Bedford County (Va.)--History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Decisions--Virginia--Bedford County.; Judicial records--Virginia--Bedford County.; Local government records--Virginia--Bedford County.
Contents List
- Judgments 1753-1755 (Barcode 1139350)
- Judgments 1755-1756 (Barcode 1139351)
- Judgments 1756-1757 (Barcode 1139352)
- Judgments 1758 (Barcode 1139353)
- Judgments 1759 (Barcode 1139354)
- Judgments 1760 (Barcode 1139355)
- Judgments 1760 (Barcode 1139356)
- Judgments 1761 (Barcode 1139357)
- Judgments 1761 (Barcode 1139358)
- Judgments 1762 (Barcode 1139359)
- Judgments 1762 (Barcode 1139360)
- Judgments 1762 (Barcode 1139361)
- Judgments 1762 (Barcode 1139362)
- Judgments 1763 (Barcode 1139363)
- Judgments 1763 (Barcode 1139364)
- Judgments 1763 (Barcode 1139365)
- Judgments 1763 (Barcode 1139366)
- Judgments 1764 (Barcode 1139367)
- Judgments 1764 (Barcode 1139368)
- Judgments 1764 (Barcode 1139369)
- Judgments 1764-1765 (Barcode 1139370)
- Judgments 1765-1767 (Barcode 1139371)
- Judgments 1767-1768 (Barcode 1139372)
- Judgments 1769 (Barcode 1139373)
- Judgments 1769 (Barcode 1139374)
- Judgments 1770 (Barcode 1139375)
- Judgments 1770 (Barcode 1139376)
- Judgments 1770 (Barcode 1139377)
- Judgments 1771 (Barcode 1139378)
- Judgments 1772 (Barcode 1139379)
- Judgments 1772 (Barcode 1139380)
- Judgments 1772 (Barcode 1139381)
- Judgments 1772 (Barcode 1139382)
- Judgments 1772 (Barcode 1139383)
- Judgments 1773 (Barcode 1139384)
- Judgments 1773 (Barcode 1139385)
- Judgments 1773 (Barcode 1139386)
- Judgments 1773 (Barcode 1139387)
- Judgments 1773-1774 (Barcode 1139388)
- Judgments 1774 (Barcode 1139389)
- Judgments 1774 (Barcode 1139390)
- Judgments 1778 (Barcode 1139391)
- Judgments 1778-1779 (Barcode 1139392)
- Judgments 1779 (Barcode 1139393)
- Judgments 1783 (Barcode 1139394)
- Judgments 1784 (Barcode 1139395)
- Judgments 1784 (Barcode 1139396)
- Judgments 1784 (Barcode 1139397)
- Judgments 1784 (Barcode 1139398)
- Judgments 1785 (Barcode 1139399)
- Judgments 1785 (Barcode 1139400)
- Judgments 1785 (Barcode 1139401)
- Judgments 1785 (Barcode 1139402)
- Judgments 1786 (Barcode 1139403)
- Judgments 1786 (Barcode 1139404)
- Judgments 1786 (Barcode 1139405)
- Judgments 1786-1787 (Barcode 1139406)
- Judgments 1787 (Barcode 1139407)
- Judgments 1787-1788 (Barcode 1139408)
- Judgments 1788 (Barcode 1139409)
- Judgments 1788 (Barcode 1139410)
- Judgments 1789 (Barcode 1139411)
- Judgments 1789 (Barcode 1139412)
- Judgments 1789 (Barcode 1139413)
- Judgments 1789-1790 (Barcode 1139414)
- Judgments 1790 (Barcode 1139415)
- Judgments 1790-1791 (Barcode 1139416)
- Judgments 1791 (Barcode 1139417)
- Judgments 1791-1792 (Barcode 1139418)
- Judgments 1792 (Barcode 1139419)
- Judgments 1793 (Barcode 1139420)
- Judgments 1793 (Barcode 1139421)
- Judgments 1793 (Barcode 1139422)
- Judgments 1794 (Barcode 1139423)
- Judgments 1794 (Barcode 1139424)
- Judgments 1794 (Barcode 1139425)
- Judgments 1794-1795 (Barcode 1139426)
- Judgments 1795 (Barcode 1139427)
- Judgments 1795 (Barcode 1139428)
- Judgments 1795-1796 (Barcode 1139429)
- Judgments 1796 (Barcode 1139430)
- Judgments 1796 (Barcode 1139431)
- Judgments 1797 (Barcode 1139432)
- Judgments 1797 (Barcode 1139433)
- Judgments 1798 (Barcode 1139434)
- Judgments 1798-1799 (Barcode 1139435)
- Judgments 1799 (Barcode 1139436)
- Judgments 1799 (Barcode 1139437)
- Judgments 1800-1830 (Barcode 1157713)
- Judgments 1833-1870 (Barcode 1157714)